A Guide to the Charles Clifton Penick Papers, 1837-1914
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Charles Clifton Penick Papers, 1837-1956
The Library of Virginia
50987
4.775 cubic feet (11 boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchased.
Biographical Information
Charles Clifton Penick was born in Charlotte County, Virginia on 9 December 1843. He was the son of Edwin Anderson Penick (1820-1862) and Mary Morris Hamner (1821-1881). He attended military school in Danville, Virginia, and soon afterward he went to Hampden-Syidney College. At the beginning of the Civil War, he joined the Confederate army and served with the 38th Virginia Infantry. He then entered the Theological seminary of Virginia at Alexandria, and was graduated in 1869. He was ordained deacon in the chapel of the seminary on 26 June 1869, and as priest on 24 June 1870. Rev. Penick served in Bristol, Virginia, and then in Mount Savage, Maryland. Three years later he accepted the rectorship of the Church of the Messiah in Baltimore, which post he held until 1877. Having been appointed missionary bishop of Cape Palmas and Parts Adjacent in western Africa, he was consecrated in St. Paul's Church, Alexandria, Virginia, on 13 February 1877. He received the degree of D. D. from Kenyon College in Ohio, in 1877. After six years' service in Africa, he sent in his resignation, which was accepted by the House of Bishops in 1883. Afterwards, Bishop Penick served in rectorships at St. Andrew's Church (Louisville, KY), St. Mark's (Richmond, VA), Christ Church (Fairmont, WV), and in Frankfort, KY. He married Mary E. Hoge (1845-1912) in Wheeling, West Virginia on 28 April 1881. Charles Clifton Penick died on 13 April 1914 at Enoch Pratt Hospital in Baltimore, where he had gone for medical treatment. He is buried in the St. John's Episcopal Church cemetery in Halifax, Virginia.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1837-1956, of Bishop Charles Clifton Penick (1843-1914) of Halifax County, Virginia, containing material relating to his service as Bishop of the Jurisdiction of Cape Palmas and Parts Adjacent, West Africa, including accounts and expenses, copies of minutes of the mission, letterbook of outgoing correspondence, and reports to the General Convention of the Protestant Episcopal Church. There are also almanacs and diaries kept by Bishop Penick, correspondence, estate papers, patent papers, published works, scrapbooks, sermons, and tax records.
There is a good deal of correspondence from 1893 concerning a circular letter written by Penick entitled "The Negro and the Christian in the United States: A Study of the Census of 1890." Many of the letters are written to Penick by fellow clergymen expressing their views on Penick's opinions. The letters also relate to his appointment as general agent on the Church Commission for Work Among Colored People.
The collection also includes various scrapbooks. The first is from the Susanne Rochet Chapter of the Huguenot Society of the Founders of Manakin in the Colony of Virginia compiled by its founder, Elizabeth Alexander (Green) Penick (1887-1945). The second is a scrapbook of a Caribbean cruise sponsored by the Twenty-First Street Businessmen's Association of Norfolk, Virginia. compiled by Lucy Mead (Allen) Wilkinson (1885-1960). Finally, there are three scrapbooks containing newspaper clipppings relating to World War II by an unknown compiler.
There are also papers relating to a patent issued to Penick for a fan attachment for a baby carriage in 1897, and to Alexander Ridley Green (1841-1906) for a car-truck, issued in 1899. There is correspondence, specifications, and rough drawings.
Finally, there is an unpublished manuscript written by Cornelius Tacitus Allen (1841-1919) in 1904, while he was living in Audrain County, Missouri, expressing his views and opinions on why the South seceded from the Union, and fought the Federal armies for four years. The volume is not complete, and the pagination varies. For preservation reasons, the entire work has been photocopied.
Contents List
- Account Book, 1875-1880. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Accounts and Receipts 1875-1880. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- African Steam-Ship Company - Rates of Freight, 1877. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Agreements. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Allen, Cornelius Tacitus - Manuscript. (Box 1, Folder 5-9)
- Almanacs, 1879-1883. (Box 1, Folder 10-14)
- Arizona Ostrich Company. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Bible Readings, nos. 1-12 and unnumbered,1886-1897. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Boyd, James. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Calendar, 1949. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Cancelled Checks. (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Cash Account Book, 1869-1883. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Catechism/Christian Doctrine. (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Commission for Church Work Among Colored People - Minutes, 28 February 1893. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Commonplace Book. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Commonplace Book. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Confirmation Lectures. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Connecticut Mutual Life Insurance. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1838, 1878-1890. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1893 (January-March). (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1893 (April-May). (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1893 (June-July). (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1893 (August-December). (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1894. (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1897-1908. (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1909-1915. (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Deeds. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Diaries, 1879-1880, 1894. (Box 3, Folder 2-4)
- Elements of Heat-Power Engineering (Annotated). (Box 10, Folder n/a)
- Estate of Charles Clifton Penick. (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
- Everlasting Life: A Vision by Rev. C. Clifton Penick, 1899. (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Expenses from Africa to Wheeling, WV, 1882. (Box 3, Folder 8)
- First National Bank of Fairmont. (Box 3, Folder 9)
- The Fundamentals: A Testimony to the Truth - Volume VIII. (Box 3, Folder 10)
- General Convention Reports, 1880, 1883. (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Green, Alexander Ridley - Patent Papers. (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Holy Bible (Annotated). (Box 3, Folder n/a)
- Honorary Arms and Crest, 1956. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Horae Paulinae: Clergyman's Companion by William Paley. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Inventory of Mission Property Left in Orphan Asylum, 1878. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Journal (Accounts), 1890-1912. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Kinematics of Machinery (Annotated). (Box 10, Folder n/a)
- Lectures. (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
- Letterbook, 31 October 1878 - 9 September 1884. (Box 4, Folder n/a)
- Medical Examiner's Report - Life Insurance, 1883. (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Minutes - Cape Palmas Mission, 23 December 1837 - 20 June 1852. (Box 4, Folder 8-10)
- Miscellaneous. (Box 5, Folder 1)
- "The Negro and the Christian in the United States: A Study in the Census of 1890" by C. Clifton Penick - Circular Letter, 1 May 1893. (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Notes on Bible Verses. (Box 10, Folder n/a)
- Our Dead: Our Memories: Our Lessons: Our Duties by Rev. C. Clifton Penick, 1888. (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Patent - Fan Attachment for Baby Carriage. (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Photographs. (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Poetry/Hymns. (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Postcards. (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Scrapbook - Huguenot Society - Susanne Rochet Chapter, 1937-1942. (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Sermons, nos. 126-229. (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Sermons, nos. 259-276. (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Sermons, nos. 298-313. (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Sermons, nos. 313 (cont.)-329. (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Sermons, nos. 330-349. (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Sermons, nos. 360-366. (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Sermons, nos. 366 (cont.)-412. (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Sermons, nos. 413-425. (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Sermons, nos. 426-441. (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Sermons, nos. 444-464. (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Sermons, nos. 468-482. (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Sermons, nos. 484-498. (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Sermons, nos. 500-541. (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Sermons, nos. 548-569. (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Sermons, nos. 577-600. (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Sermons, nos. 604-618. (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Sermons, nos. 619-650. (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Sermons, nos. 651-671. (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Sermons, nos. 672-697. (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Sermons, nos. 701-746. (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Sermons, nos. 747-792. (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Sermons, nos. 793-800. (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Sermons, nos. 801-811. (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Sermons, nos. 812-822. (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Sermons, nos. 829-841. (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Sermons, nos. 842-851. (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Sermons, nos. 853-884. (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Sermons, nos. 888-900. (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Sermons, nos. 901-928. (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Sermons, nos. 1030-1038, 2331-2372. (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Sermons, nos. 1431-1440. (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Sermons, nos. 1501-1515. (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Sermons, nos. 2253-2331. (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Sermons, nos. 2701-2819. (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Sermons, nos. 2821-2940. (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Sermons, nos. 3176-3350. (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Sermons, nos. 3579-3741. (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Sermons, nos. 3742-3926. (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Sermons, unnumbered. (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Sermons, unnumbered, and Reasons for Leaving Africa. (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Sermons - Key/Index. (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Seton, Samuel Waddington. (Box 9, Folder 1)
- The Story of Goochland by Richard Cunningham Wight, 1935. (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Tax Tickets and Receipts, 1895-1905. (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Twenty-First Street Businessmen's Association Cruise - Scrapbook, 1951. (Box 9, Folder 4-6)
- World War II Scrapbooks. (Box 11, Folder n/a)